software engineering radio episode 52
DSL 0b
okay welcome over to this episode of
software engineering radio we're going
to talk about agile DSL development in
Ruby so once again this DSL stuff but
now implemented in a host language it
keeps coming up it doesn't it
yeah the DSL topic is definitely hard
yeah definitely and we've talked about
model driven development and these more
static approaches so looking at dynamic
approaches in Ruby is probably the next
next important step so let's get started
with maybe talking about what what a DSL
actually is we talked about it before
but just trying to formulate that in
your words
well the way I intend to introduce DSL
to people that haven't heard about the
concept before is to relate it to jargon
which is a concept that most people are
familiar with yeah and one of the
dictionary definitions of target is the
language especially the vocabulary
peculiar to a particular trade
profession or group yeah and that's a
very useful way of introducing the
concept of a DSL to an audience or
wherever you may be discussing it with
because everyone is familiar with
domain-specific language examples in
their day to day life even if they're
not familiar with them or they don't
recognize them as such yeah and a DSL is
simply a way of using some programming
language technology to capture that
jargon or a subset of jargon for for a
particular task in an executable form
yeah so the the the executable form is
important so it has to be formal it
there has to be some degree of formality
there has to be some way to execute it
otherwise it's just some sort of spec or
something right yeah so that's also the
difference between specs and DSL correct
yes other executable correct so and do
you want to briefly elaborate on the
difference between external and internal
DSL and why you probably think internal
the users are more useful sure internal
versus external is something that will
is introduced by Martin Fowler in the
relatively recent past perhaps last year
he wrote an article called language
workbenches yeah which we'll put into
the show notes yeah it was about
language oriented design which has to do
in part with dsls the external versus
internal distinction was one that
perhaps had not been made the same way
before I know had been described in
different ways internal is a way of
describing a domain-specific language
which is implemented within the
framework of a general-purpose
programming language
okay such as Ruby for instance or the I
think the the grandfather of all these
techniques is perhaps Lisp yeah
programming in Lisp pretty much is a
continuous exercise of building up
narrower and narrower domain-specific
languages so I guess one of the key
capabilities of a language in order to
make it useful for implementing internal
DSL is that the syntax is flexible or
tweakable or something and Ruby has a
very flexible syntax it has a very
flexible syntax most things in Ruby can
be done at least two ways yeah for
instance blocks yeah can be defined in a
typical multi-line format with do and
finishing with end or you can use curly
braces yeah the fact that you can do it
both ways actually gives you some
flexibility as a language designer as a
domain-specific language designers so so
and some people say that the reason why
why it was easy in Lisp to design TS
else's because list doesn't have a
syntax at all because you vertically
write the trees directly yeah exactly so
let's look at DSL examples there is one
that I really like it's about ordering
coffee right
yeah it's ordering coffee so for our
american listeners and wherever the
Starbucks is the predominant way to get
your caffeine fix you know that if you
walk into a Starbucks and you say venti
half-caf nonfat no-foam know what latte
they will know exactly what you mean
even though you know outside of that
context it makes absolutely no sense at
all
that was an example I gave him the talk
as my my lead into a toy example that we
had implemented a DSL so another one
might be route 66 swinging easy on the
chorus extra solo at the coda and bump
at the end and by the way these are a
couple examples that my colleague Neil
Ford also talks about DSL season one his
Auslan presentation with ESL's and I
thought they were kind of cool as
real-life yeah right
really examples yeah yeah and they also
illustrate that if you don't know the
context of the DSL the the program
probably doesn't make much sense because
I read these slides and I didn't
recognize it now I'm not American right
still I didn't know you're talking about
coffee so maybe you know it was hard to
recognize it yeah again the the fact
that it's a narrow domain but the person
that would if this was some sort of
software that we need to implement the
person validating and the person helping
to define the spec yeah the nose of his
opposition is that yes they would know
yeah
so one there's a frequently recurring
discussion about what's the difference
between a framework and a pis and fluent
api is and a DSL so how would a
traditional api based implementation of
such an api basically to order coffee
look like it's obviously a bit hard to
describe a pis and program source code
in an audible form only but we'll try so
it's just a couple lines so I give an
example of what I described is not a
particularly good API driven approach to
this but it was basically in Ruby code
latte knew and then takes three
parameters so it's just which are three
constants venti half-caf nonfat that
gets you an order yep object an instance
and then from that order you can invoke
prepare and in this case in the case of
the example in the talk I passed a false
parameter and the part of the point is
that even though this is completely
normal code when the context of my talk
part of the point is you don't know
exactly what that false is yeah
it doesn't say such-and-such equals
false it's correct there's no key word
parameters just actually passing a false
yeah so if we if we're looking at this
as someone who's not familiar with the
implementation is code we actually have
to go and look at the API in order to
understand it yeah so in the API you
would look at for instance definition of
the prepare method and see that oh it
takes two parameters ed foam and add
whip and because it's a latte
ad foam is true and I'd whip is false
yep okay I mean that's normal code and
that's very typical of what you find all
over the place yeah but actually for
maybe for you folks Java programmers it
basically looks the same because using
constants and calling the constructor
it's basically the same thing so now
let's look at how it could also look
like if we do it with a language that
does have a flexible syntax you couldn't
do that in Java right I don't think you
could do this in Java I mean you can
let's go back to that in a second yeah
okay so in the in the DSL --is-- example
in Ruby the line would literally read
latte venti comma half-caf comma nonfat
comma no foam comma no whip yeah so it
is it's almost exactly word for word
right at the description and there is no
function called parenthesis and there is
no new call so it doesn't look like
exercise it doesn't look like a program
it doesn't necessarily look like a
program you can because I've included
for instance underscores hmm which
didn't need to be there but it just you
know what was the way that that came out
the napkin kind of tell that it's sort
of vaguely programming like yeah in fact
that uh in the example for instance I I
signed it to an order okay things like
that but even to a non programming
person yes who was on my team as a
perhaps domain expert or business
analyst yeah if I sat him down next to
me we talked about the principles of
agile is to include people in the
process right yes and and I said this is
look right he would read it and he would
say yeah that looks right yeah even the
person who is completely intimidated by
programming in general yeah which we've
met we meet those on the yeah yeah yeah
and we can bring them in and perhaps
it's um coaxingly said can you please
look at this yeah and this is a really
interesting point you make because I've
mentioned that before I don't think it
is very realistic to have the real
domain experts actually write the code
right but if you do pairing if you do
pair programming with a domain expert
and you have a notation that doesn't put
him off as soon as he sees it that's a
big advantage already it's a huge
advantage yeah so you don't have to talk
about specs so so how do you go go
forward if you design a Ruby DSL is
there like like process or best practice
of steps that you'll do yeah this is
from our practice yeah so we've done
this a couple times on other projects in
that works the advice that I gave that I
give actually is don't try to do your
abstract metamodel first yeah that would
be the the process of going through
analysis upfront and a trying to create
a class model yeah and the object model
that you're gonna base your DSL on yeah
so don't do that first yeah I say
together with the domain expert or the
you're an analyst capture your DSL
concepts and value invalid Ruby syntax
yeah so if you're a Ruby beginner you
may have a bit of difficulty with this
yes and if you're not a particular good
particularly good writer for instance a
V you don't express yourself very well
in writing yeah you may have a little
bit of problem with this yeah correct
there's some there's some underlying
prerequisites that are necessary to be
able to use this technique however if
you if you can write a little bit if you
understand the dynamics of language
design a little bit and you know valid
Ruby syntax then you're ready to go yep
you can basically sit down and have a
conversation a dialogue with the user to
you know or whoever's driving your yep
your domain yeah
and just say well what what are the
requirements that we're going to cover
so for instance if we were trying to
implement some business
for our application as a DSL let's
describe some of these business rules
and we may just start by capturing the
vocabulary yeah yeah that that would be
the the process of starting to develop
an ontology yeah yeah yeah what is what
is this jargon what are the what's the
lexicon of this jargon yeah we put those
down and it's very very easy as actually
I showed I think in some of the you know
for instance with the latte example it's
very very easy to put down code without
worrying about the implementation and
you can even check the Ruby syntax to
make sure it's okay yeah and and you can
just iterate over that so there's like
example or even test-driven right so you
start with the the test case first and
then you implement the language we'll
talk about that later until it works
yeah sometimes it's more than one expert
you want to run it by yeah oftentimes it
is a it is an exercise of analysis
because you have to find if the if
you're doing it in DSL rather than hard
coding things just in a traditional
sense there's got to be some driver for
that so what we found is that it's it's
quite often advantageous to use DSL in
order to capture the business rules yeah
which are mostly common but they vary
yep so in the case of the bank that we
worked with we were capturing business
rules related to how they compensate
their partners yeah and the thing is
that they mostly compensated their
partners in very similar ways but every
single partner had a contract which was
negotiated and independently yeah and
had little quirks and little differences
that made it unique from the others so
in this case you describe the contracts
with these rules formally at as a DSL um
not asked just a Word document
correct they had many Excel documents
and Word documents and actually the
contract itself yeah which they were
using to do their analysis and basically
plug in these business rules I say with
air quotes yeah because it wasn't truly
a rule space system it was just a custom
PLC column
patien yep of a rules-based system yeah
and part of the problem is that the
errors can cost a lot of money because
you have no good way other than by
running the the beast and checking the
results of seeing is this correct
according to the contract yeah that you
don't have it so on the left side you
may have your contract right in language
the spec if you will on the right side
you don't have anything you have a bunch
of PL sequel which doesn't make any
sense anyway except who wrote it yeah so
in this case we went through and created
the SL which match the contract language
as closely as we yeah you know we
thought we could do it yeah so now on
the left side you have your contract on
the right side you have your DSL script
yeah and now you have something to
relate to correct and we'll put probably
some of these slides into the show notes
and we should yeah one thing that I that
is really cool I'm looking at this at
this moment that you can actually treat
numbers as objects and then write $5 in
order to express that it's not just five
it's actually five dollars so this is
this is actually cool so we'll put more
of these in them in the show notes so I
get the impression that writing to
yourselves in Ruby is quite a natural
way of working with Ruby in fact many
people say and I'd agree there of course
that Ruby on Rails the result at the
Ruby these days maybe is actually a DSL
for web development right its collection
of DSL all right yeah around yeah around
the whole process of developing web apps
yeah yeah so yeah it's important too
it's important to note that calling
rails itself a big DSL is only true in
the most abstract sense yeah addresses
several domains like presentation and
transactions so it's it's a collection
the point is that yet for its I think
it's very important for people to
realize that if your DSL is too
encompassing if it v spans yeah too many
are even if it's too big within a
certain domain yes
to suffer it's going to suffer because
the the language that use even within a
particular domain the semantics of that
language is very dependent on context
yeah
although the I love you would be that
it's like a philosophical discussion
whether you say there is one big DSL
that has several partitions for the role
at four different aspects of the problem
or whether you say you have several DSL
that you combine together order to solve
a bigger problem that's like the usual
discard yeah the point is that the
different aspects of complex systems
require different syntax different that
are models different formalisms that's
correct and and I would say rails proves
that true yeah the one of the key
differentiators being that it's all Ruby
yeah so whereas in other systems in
other ways of putting together web app
for instance even if you had fluent
interfaces there may be a combination of
different technologies yes many many
different flavors of XML so on and so
forth it's probably two reasons why this
works and in Ruby one is the syntactic
sugar so the flexible syntax and the
other thing is Ruby's meta programming
facilities yes I think we should talk
about these now to get the feeling for
our listeners how to actually implement
it yourself because writing down stuff
not all so what are some of the
syntactic sugar elements that make DSL
development it will be easy well one of
the first things is the the fact that
the parentheses are optional mmm very
very important because the fact that I
can leave off parenthesis when I call a
method mm-hmm it lets language flow much
more naturally it lets it be less
intimidating to a non programmer so on
and so forth yeah less line noise hmm
and if you strive for simplicity in your
DSL design then you'll want to live
leave off any unnecessary parenthesis
just to let it read closer to natural
language correct yeah another thing to
that that's very important and useful is
the fact that in Ruby we use symbols
which are basically in turn strings as
names as identifier z' and symbols are
denoted with a colon along
so basically any string that starts with
a colon that's a symbol yeah and just to
add to that I'm since Ruby is a dynamic
language and you don't have compiled or
static typing in for example in your
editor there is no real difference
between writing a keyword a method call
and a symbol because it's all kind of
the same thing it's only at operative
runtime right that's why you can make
symbols method calls and things kind of
without noticing it yeah as long as it's
valid syntax of course yes you know and
you get used it there may be some
discomfort I would say coming over from
from a Java background with with things
being like that you know in the way that
you describe the fact that you mix all
these things together in many different
ways yeah this the syntax is a bit
looser yeah but it deals a lot of
benefits for DSL you know what we were
talking about that went as far as syntax
sugar the blocks yeah for instance very
very valuable a block is essentially a
there's different ways to describe it
but it is a closure and basically it's a
function anonymous it's an anonymous
function that you can pass around you
can assign it to a variable and many
methods in Ruby or methods that you
define yourself can take a block yeah
and like they did the block can be
optional yeah which is useful
yeah and then the block lets you delay
execution okay so the contact put it
somewhere hand it around there are
executed later yes absolutely so for
some of the Java programmers who
unfortunately don't have this feature in
their language it's more it's maybe like
a command pattern with a lot of
syntactic sugar yeah because a lot of
times you you're just going to need that
particular command implementation just
once yeah so you don't want to extract
it somewhere else you want it in lines
it actually has the context for you to
understand it without having to define
an anonymous inner class well yeah x
value becomes noise yeah you can't do
this yeah so the next thing that I saw
in in Ruby is
like literal hashes and literal arrays
where you again leave away the parents
and therefore the fact that well literal
arrays are our presence in Java yeah
literal hashes are not yep and and
actually this is this is one of my
favorite features of everything yet the
fact that you can very very elegantly I
think pass around just these literal
hash yeah you know using a notation
where you use a little arrow symbols so
that's the you know equals greater than
yeah and it's just so beautiful you know
for cases where you need to pass things
that look like keyword arguments right
exactly yeah you know so for instance
going back to my we were discussing the
fact that Ruby programming in general
tends towards dsls
kind of things right I went back to my
original coffee example and I wanted to
improve that by making it a little bit
more dsl ish yeah I may change the
method signature of asphalt thing right
yeah the false thing so that when I call
prepare instead of having just two
normal arguments like fault and true
right I would pass a hash yeah and the
hash would use symbols as keys yeah to
say add whip and add foam yeah and I
would so I would actually say I'd whip
arrow true yeah so the point is that
that in that case the the person that
came along and had to maintain that code
or had to verify that that code is
correct would actually read in and have
the context there and it would be more
expressive yeah that's really the key
and in striving for and again for the
static language person this sounds
strange because are you loose type
safety and you have this hash as a
parameter but but in the end in Ruby
doesn't matter since everything is
dynamic it doesn't matter whether you
pass arguments that are not checked at
run at compile time or in the editor or
whether you pass a hash because both are
not checked so both are kind of the same
level of guarantee statically which is
basically not yeah if you need to
enforce some contract on those
parameters then you do so and we quite
often do so you basically check like if
there is
in NASH and if it is in fact the way
that many rails methods are implemented
is that they they take very varying
different types yeah you know for
instance the fine method this is one of
the most basic things you can do with
rails is to use the active record
framework to find the record the fine
method on active record takes an ID so
basically if it receives in America is
the first parameter it will look up that
row by ID yeah if it receives the
keyword expressed with the symbol first
it will return the first row hmm you get
my point
you can it can be polymorphic in terms
of the parameters is varied and you know
it's very different than what we're used
to in Java and that's one there's
examples that I give for instance that
so many things in rails are just very
good examples of DL and DSL ish type
code you know very expressive code yeah
I want to emphasize that the the key
point here is not to create a DSL for
the sake of creating a DSL yeah it's
it's a whole philosophy it's a whole
mentality about how you you write your
code in expressive fashion so the
example we just have in front of us is
like you can take a class you can add a
keyword like act as state machine and
then you can define States and the point
is that making a class act as a state
machine actually has to change the
behavior of the class there might be
something like
trigger and then something has to move
so we as a consequence of writing state
and then : stalled for example where :
stalled as a symbol you have to actually
modify the class as a consequence which
brings us to meta programming and house
modification yeah right so let's let's
look talk about some of these features
then I guess there's a there's a really
good quote by James Bach who was
well-known figure in the rails community
it works for 37signals has contributed a
lot to rails including Capistrano which
is our deployment framework so he said
the trick to writing DSL and Ruby is
really knowing what you can and can't do
it Ruby's many programming features
mm-hm yeah like you were saying the butt
part of what makes us possible to work
in this way and to make it so expressive
is the fact that for instance in that
example when I say access state machine
and then give it its initial State
yeah there's a lot going on under the
scenes there's a it's not subtle at all
there's methods being created there's
being changed
you know there's database columns that
will be accessed now you know so and and
and this is one of the really cool
things that I was really glad to see in
Ruby when I took a look at it first so
you have to picture this you define a
class such-and-such like for example
class story subclasses extends gold and
then you can literally write acts as
state machine and this what looks like
just a keyword is actually a method call
that is evaluated upon class definition
and then as a consequence changes the
class right yeah as as this classes is
getting initialized you can execute
methods on it that have been mixed in or
that come from up from a superclass yeah
and those methods can contribute to the
you know construction of that class and
its behavior by adding methods and merit
to it in the end it's self-modifying
code right yeah which is historically at
some point sometimes well but I mean
they're also referred to as higher-order
functions because they're functions that
you know create other functions yeah
yeah okay so let's look at the set of
features that are typically used for
building to yourself better programming
features there's definitely different
ways of creating dsls and and the
particular way that these were
identified it was I think in a blog
posting my James Bach
yeah so he he went through and said okay
well it's just I see four different ways
and I happened to agree with him so the
first one is instantiation is simply a
DSL that is composed of methods on an
object and builder is an example of this
builder by Jim why Rick was a legend in
the Ruby community is a very very good
little API for building XML
and the way that works is that you
create an XML markup object and since we
just part of the Builder library yeah
now you have this reference and you
capture that in a variable yeah
which we normally call XML frog screams
mmm okay and then the this builder
object has a couple of special methods
for instance like instruct bang yeah
the bang denote said it's a special
method there's something going on there
and it basically generates and instructs
tag near the top but then everything
else it doesn't really have any other
methods other than a method missing yeah
callback method missing for those not
familiar with the concept is all objects
in Ruby end up with them with the method
missing yeah you know method but
inherited yeah and what that does is it
throws an exception yeah which says I
don't have this method so so what
happens is in your client code you call
a method that doesn't exist on the class
yes on the object and then yeah and then
the callback is invoked and then you can
react yeah so normally objects
definition of method missing is to throw
an exception you override it right in
your when you override it you make it
for instance in this case we'd builder
to say okay I'll take whatever method
you called and use that as the name of
the tag hat that I want to create yeah
and probably then return the Builder
object again so yes and correct
recursively our repeatedly it also
leverages the fact that Ruby blocks you
know are so so powerful you can pass
your content your execution context
around yeah so the fact that I nest
using a block structure again further
calls xml creates nested structures in
my in my decimal and and again to the
java programmer it's it looks strange
because you call a method that's not
there and the java compiler would simply
say hey compile time error doesn't work
but here because everything is executed
or evaluated at runtime it's just
something you can react to at runtime
yeah it's very very different than than
a frame based language where the methods
have to be known yeah
Ruby's is message
into just like small talk so the even
though you define methods on a class
whenever you you are invoking a method
you're basically sending a message yeah
I never really got the difference
between sending a message and invoking
the invoking a method its philosophical
I guess yeah probably a topic for
another time but the point is that
because it's treated in that way you can
have message handling for unknown
messages right you know which which
enables this kind of thing yeah so class
macros is a different way of achieving
is the same kind of result DSL results
of expressive code this is use very very
widely in rails yes
belongs to as many yeah it's what we
were talking about a few minutes ago as
far as defining methods at the class
level which you then invoke in friends
and subclasses yeah like you said I
access state machine for instance is one
that you can mix in and here for
instance we see an example of a rule set
something I pulled out of one of my
existing projects yeah belongs to global
criteria belongs to a partner has many
comments and these things get executed
as the classes initialize and it goes
through series of behavior because of
that and it changes the structure of the
class to again picture this you have a
class it extends from some base class or
it mixes in some kind of mixin and then
you can call the methods that this
superclass has in it static methods you
can call them and as part of the
definition of the class you're currently
working in this method is executed and
it can do whatever it wants do what
everyone's for example use things like
instance eval or class a value to
actually modify the class that's
currently created on the fly yes this is
actually really pretty cool yeah and
like a metal object protocol in C lost
and stuff yes yeah absolutely and then
and later on we'll get into even cooler
stuff you can do like for instance read
part of the class division from a
database so now you're mixing the you
know your data is code and your code is
data and all sorts of fun stuff like
that yeah
another way of implementing a DSL and
Ruby is to use top-level methods so this
is more appropriate to the person that's
building some sort of utility or so
top-level methods you mean are not
associated with a class
well there's there is one con there is a
main in execution context at the
beginning of execution of a ruby program
so if for instance you define methods in
that context then they'll be available
in that top-level context yeah
the main example of this is rake rake is
the build tool Ruby's make yeah Ruby's
make and we use it in the same way that
you would use ant yeah in Java
no wonder why people didn't call it R
and I've seen I've seen some called rant
actually that tried to be more like ant
okay but Jim why Rick I said before is a
legend it's a very talented guy wrote
this thing called rake and it's
beautiful mm-hmm and it is an example of
a DSL is targeted at the domain of the
building you know so it doesn't I
remember that the first time I heard
rake described as a DSL kind of struck
me as odd mm-hmm because I'm used to
thinking of DSL zazz throwing as leaning
more towards natural language you know
exclusivity but the point is that
someone who is thinking and working the
domain of building software yes it is an
it is an agile Mesa yeah exactly that's
why usually distinguish between
technical domains and business or
functional domains and make a rake a
building would be a technical domain
correct so in order to use rake
basically you just include rakes methods
you know it basically sets up the
context and then you just suck in your
script and load it and then it gets
executed yeah and I showed the the
audience an example of a custom task
from one of my projects finds a
namespace describes it gives the
description wide database task action
task clear depends on environment and
then takes a block for what to do and it
depends on is written as a
as a hash basically again yeah right
past such-and-such and then the arrow
and then another task name correct
that's really nice yeah
so I you see that there's a little bit
of a mental mapping going on there
because I in fact I don't even think
about it but when I read task clean the
clean arrow environment right I read as
clean depends on environment yeah and
there's a bit of that mapping that
actually you can teach your domain
experts in your analysts yeah to
understand that little little bits of
Ruby syntax for instance like the arrow
to mean as or especially if those people
don't know Ruby in the first place so
they don't have to replace the meaning
they already know for the symbol with
something else it's just the child I
mean this means this now sometimes I say
you know with with Ruby DSL this how far
down the rabbit hole do you want to go
hmm because for instance Jay fields it
was a very good friend of mine it works
and and one of the guys that's been
pioneering some of this stuff with me
yeah we can for instance replace that
arrow there with as with the word as you
can do that in Ruby I mean there's
there's there's ways basically to use
method missing and often the primers
that are passed to that and get the same
exact result yeah yeah but do you need
to do that mmm right so there's two you
know there's trade-offs in terms of the
complexity and the implementation and
this applies is a universal rule yeah so
inst going towards natural language
style in your DSL be careful that you're
not you know sacrificing the the
elegance of your code by kookiness
incredibly complex implementation of it
just to get one little step further and
along the natural language there are
other words you have to balance that the
convenience for the dsl user with a
complexity in the effort to implement
Cariah
and this is probably something that is
somewhat unique to this whole issue of
creating internal dsls because you're
relying on an existing syntax so the
question is how much do i want to
include and how much do i want to
of break through that abstraction layer
by including elements of the underlying
programming language whereas in an
external you would have 100% control so
you're all that always making those
decisions but still you you have to you
have to trade off the amount that the in
general did the power of the DSL and you
know the the amount of exceptions to
standard behavior it can handle you have
to balance that with the amount of
effort you put into building all the
infrastructure oh yeah and that love was
the same I agree so the next one is
sandboxing our context right yeah so
this is the way that for the most part
when we're talking about using DSL in a
business context yeah it's typically in
the sense of let's write a script that
describes some business rules or some
business logic which can be directly
influenced if not written and maintained
by the business by the end-user or by
the domain expert and then what we do is
we take that and we execute in different
contexts mm-hmm
it's the same Ruby code we don't have to
transform it in any way but just
depending on what class you know context
you you execute it in you know it does
different things yeah and the example a
good example is Capistrano always
implemented in this way which is this
deployment tool this deployment tool for
rails which means you don't have to for
instance like in the Builder example we
prepended XML dot to it to everything up
but if you do things this way by being
fancy with your bindings and and the
block context of things get executed in
you can leave that off so your for
instance the one of the example
deployment tasks that that's included
with all the top external recipes is the
is a transactional deployment so tasks
deploy do transaction do update code
disable web symlink migrate and it's
it's a very readable
and a very very little noise there and
to do is actually the keyword that
introduces block yeah
the do is a keyword that introduces
block and the cop there's there's
different contexts there and they're all
linked together in a way that produces
you know some state which will you will
then execute as I started to mention
before you can keep bits and pieces of
DSL scripts in the database okay
and this is something that I've found
personally extraordinarily easy to abuse
and have fun with I would say in rails
yeah associating little bits of the
Acela SH type script that modifies the
behavior of for instance active record
objects and storing that in the database
and loading it in it at runtime and
that's of course mainly a way of getting
around some of the limitations by the
deployment folks who say you can deploy
only once a week and you want to do you
know faster changes oh you're lucky if
they say once a week once a month right
yeah or once a quarter you can tweak
stuff in and they think it's data that's
what it's one of the clever you know
that's one of the loopholes that you can
use in certain organizations if you need
to and it can be quite effective and
actually it can be safe as well because
that little snippet of executable code
can even though it's in Ruby you can put
constraints around it to make sure that
it you know it is secure and it's not
gonna present a problem to you yeah you
know rolling out what is in essence live
production code it just happens to be
stored in the database there's some
funny issues around that but you you
would typically implement that by using
this technique of earth contact sort of
sandboxing as jamester first yeah and
then the funny thing is that in creating
those contacts like we I think we
mentioned earlier you would TDD those
yeah and in TD doing them you would go
through and try to you basically start
from the beginning of your script and
and make it your script work yeah TD
deaiing by the by the way stands for
using a test-driven process to and
develop it yeah test-driven design so
we've written our DSL script which is
basically the acceptance that represents
when our script runs the way we intended
to
then this feature that you know this
this task is done yeah that's our
acceptance criteria it's a high level
executable accepting script that sense
and in order to implement that we have
to start writing the context of the
methods that will be invoked yep so on
and so forth
but we don't just write those blinds
right we begin writing unit tests for
context yeah in driving the
implementation and using unit tests now
you create a meta model yep because now
you end up with it with an object model
that represents what you need to support
your DSL script and one of the reasons
that I consider this agile is because
you don't go above and beyond what you
need to support in your script yeah yeah
you know you you do only what you need
to support the different instances of
the script that's why it's important to
do a number of different scripts and
basically consider different
possibilities yeah but here's where you
don't trip yourself up as much in terms
of refactoring mmm in future so
considering changes that may happen to
that language if you've spent a
considerable amount of time and money in
essence going through a bunch of
analysis creating a big object model
that's gonna consider the possibilities
of front
now you've encoded the assumptions that
you made in that meta model into your
DSL and it turns out that some of those
assumptions were wrong as they will be
you know that then that's gonna have a
bunch of impact on your existing code
yeah but if you only do enough to
support the existing DSL stuff that
you've verified actually does Express
the intent of the domain expert yeah
then chances are and actually I can I
can say this from experience with our
projects as things come up afterwards
there will be extensions yeah there will
be growth of the language and money
changes yes right yeah that's my
experience too and that mitigates the
you know the impact of having to
refactor DSL and evolve the schema I
dragged on in terms of meta model so
yeah so before we wrap up I think it's
it's useful
to quickly look at some of the like
supporting features that that you need
in order to define yourselves for
example I could imagine that if you want
to define methods dynamically ruby has
to provide some means of probably
evaluating a string and making this
actually source code or something like
that yeah and like I said before there
there is for almost everything in Ruby a
couple different ways of doing it
so they're there different ways of eval
at runtime yeah it's almost macro
functionality yeah eval just straight
eval
there's performance considerations there
so these are not beginner Ruby topics I
would say it's a get some you know Ruby
experience under your belt and
definitely you know get it there's
material available out there to see you
know what are the performance
implications of using eval what are the
performance of cases using instance you
know what what's instance evil and class
evil and eval they have to do with what
what the actual execution context you
want to be in your Ruby code for
instance evil modifies an object class
evil modify the class yes essentially
we could talk another half hour about
the subtleties of those probably
shouldn't and then you have things that
are relatively simple to understand like
define method hmm to define a method and
you give it define a method pass in a
block or yes correct
the block becomes the body of the method
so basically you're okay hmm
alias method to do a little bit of AOP
style things where you can just have an
existing method for instance you say
well because of this configuration for
instance let's say a class level oh you
know method call yeah well I'm gonna
alias some existing method to wrap it so
I Ilias the original method to something
old and then I go ahead and create a new
method the new method that's something I
then called the alias other method and
correct mm-hmm
it's actually funny I find it funny
because when I was I was in Java for a
long time and like for instance AOP was
a big deal a lot of people you know
still to this day argue back and forth
about whether it's good whether it's bad
when is it gonna come around when it's
gonna come over but AOP concepts and
things like this are already baked into
ruby they're like not a big deal yeah
yeah that's you know and what we do from
day to day we talked about that
yesterday evening and by the way again
we're recording this at the Joe
conference in Denmark and Aarhus in
October 2006 we talked about this over
the beer yesterday in the bar how
revolutionary and important and
groundbreaking AOP really is or is it
just may basically work around around
the limitations of Java and similar
languages right yeah yeah yeah I think
so yeah I think I'm the moderator I'm
not you know I'm saying I think I think
is important yeah but I think maybe they
make too big a deal about it and those
communities whereas now that I've been
part of the Ruby community for a while I
realized wow this is just another tool
in the tool set that they are using for
years yeah yeah yeah if we if we want to
talk about a little bit about just you
can take the these business natural
language so I should say what business
central languages first yeah this is
natural language Jay fields came up with
a catchy thing he said the damp not dry
yeah descriptive and natural phrases
yeah
so the in business and like we talked
about variations in different contracts
where they're mostly the same what they
have slight differences and naive
programmers all right well I shouldn't
even say naive say beginner typical
Enterprise type projects you know you
you end up with a lot of copy-paste
programming yeah which many of us you
know look down our noses at us yeah this
is horrible this violates all principles
and that in so many ways it's not
maintainable there's problems with that
but if you take a pragmatic approach and
you look at it you say there's very
valid reasons why sometimes enterprise
developers go for that and it's not just
laziness it's the fact that it's very
easy for instance when I'm rolling on a
new partner to say well this one is just
like partner X except with these slight
differences so let me copy the
configuration of Pyrex
and I think the differences and it saves
me work actually so by creating dsls to
capture business roles in that sense and
if you create a framework around an
application framework for people to
easily be able to cloned ya and clone is
a little bit less of a negative
connotation than copy/paste you know in
that context but essentially saying the
same thing and you put some workflow
around it and then you put some
versioning and you give tool support in
the form of syntax checking for instance
and then in this in the form of semantic
checking so I did ask the audience kind
of rhetorically how crazy do you want to
get because you know in in one sense
this go this flouts the conventional
wisdom of the vendors and you know lots
of the way that people typically
approach these types of problems you
know most conventional wisdom I would
say is it would look at a problem like
the one that we tackled you know a few
months ago using this approach and say
well of course bio and off-the-shelf
business rules you know are you or used
rules or something like that
but that's you know there's things that
you get from that but then there's a
bunch of trade-offs that you make as
well right yeah and if we are trying to
make all of our code and all you know
all of our implementation very elegant
and very expressive and very verifiable
in the ways that we've been discussing
for the last hour you know maybe you
don't want to go that route maybe you do
it yourself yeah yeah and that's where
having a you know powerful tool kit like
rails for instance in order to do it
ourselves you know and do it in 40 lines
of code yeah exaggerating but you know
the the point is that it makes so many
things so easy yeah that actually lets
you go off and be more creative in this
directions yeah yeah you know and still
come in under time under budget it comes
back to the point that I think languages
and language design and being able to
extend languages to define relevant
abstractions is really something that
it's maybe more important than using X
number of frameworks and technologies so
it's probably underestimated yeah I
think there's a lot of room for growth
yeah there's a lot of room for for
creativity and innovation and having
this
right now yeah okay so I think let's
wrap it up
yeah thank you Marcus thank you for
being on the show and we'll put a couple
of links to some of your blog's and
slide and tap into the show notes yeah
thanks again
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se
- radio net although we prefer entries
in our comment system on the website so
other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details